[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host jaavan as proni and
today I will be discussing team
topologies with Matthew Skelton Matthew
is a leader in mod organizational
Dynamics for fast flow
drawing on team topologies and adapt
together to support organizations with
transformation towards a sustainable
fast flow of value he's the co-author of
the book team topologies and CEO of
conflu and team topologies Matthew
welcome to the software engineering
radio show is there anything am miss
that you need to add that all sounds
good it's good to be here thanks for
good to be talking to you again yes
thank you for being here now well let's
start with Team topology so the question
obviously has to be what is team
topologies team topologies is I think
it's fair to say the leading approach to
organizing for a fast flow of value team
of teams organizations is the focus and
it came out of the it space but really
it's actually applicable to all
knowledge work so far this is what we
found out about we can explore this a
little bit later but because of the way
that we in the Teens polities book
didn't really zoom into into particular
Technologies it turns out that the
approach is actually really suitable for
thinking about all kinds of knowledge
work not just sort of software delivery
and it but other things as well so you
could really see it teties as an
approach to knowledge work where we're
using technology to enhance our
capabilities as humans to do knowledge
work really effectively at scale okay
now I know that the model is based on
four theme types and three interaction
modes can you briefly describe them to
us
yeah but I don't think that's the best
place to start so that's how we talk
about it in the book but actually
there's a danger if you start with just
types of team and interaction modes that
that people really take a very shallow
reading of team polities they just see
it in terms of structure in terms of
like renaming some teams so it's
actually important to go a step
backwards and look at what's behind the
principles underneath teams apologies
the principles really are we're trying
to get to a position where we've got a
fast flow value out towards the user
and we are going to have multiple
separate flows of value because we're
trying to go quickly so we're
deliberately decoupling these flows
we're not trying to bring them all
together and coordinate them so some
large scale software delivery agile
Frameworks try to coordinate everything
together but we're deliberately
decoating in order to get a fast flow we
need to be mindful of Team size because
we want to have high trust so we can go
quickly so then the size of the team is
quite small that's involved we take the
team as the smallest unit of delivery by
the way like we don't go down into
individuals when we're thinking about
the roles and responsibilities we need
to think about the cognitive load or
mental load on that team because they're
going to be building and running a
service a single kind of stream of value
that's useful to a user they're going to
be building and running that thing on an
ongoing basis and to be able to look
after something like that with all the
different aspects that you need to think
about in terms of building and running
something we've got to be mindful of the
cognitive load that we're placing people
under because otherwise they just won't
be able to support it properly we've got
to think about the kind of system and
organizational architectures that work
really well for flow if we're going to
have multiple fast flows of value then
there's only a certain small number of
kind of architectures that actually work
well we've got to be mindful of what's
called conways law which is like a
mirroring between the organizational
communication Pathways and the likely
architecture that results from that and
this has been it's a tendency it's a
kind of force that's at play if you like
we can choose to work against it but
it's going to be more difficult if we
work against that what's called
homomorphic Force so we've got to be
mindful that that the shape of our
organization communication Pathways is
likely to influence the kind of systems
that we end up building we need to be
mindful that any digital technology we
introduce now is likely to be obsolete
in five years three years 18 months so
the way in which we think about
introducing technology and using
technology needs to expect it to
disappear within a very short space of
time which is quite extreme compared to
how Technologies was used in previous
decades so you are actually suggesting
teams to actually plan for that as well
like plan for the fact that Technologies
are going to change is one of the things
have cuz this is where organizations get
into a fix they expect they'll introduce
new technology they'll get 10 years
worth of life out of it it's not like
that anymore we might introduce a
technology to give us an 18month
advantage and then beyond 18 months that
technology might actually start to act
like a drag and we need to be expecting
to replace that technology with
something that we're just getting from a
cloud provider so teties provides the
underlying fundamental kind of mindset
and dynamics that allow us to have true
like business agility to organizational
agility in the context of Technology
changing very rapidly and in the context
where we've got the techniques and
practices where we can deliver software
changes you know hundreds of times every
day and that's table Stakes to be honest
for many organizations to be able to do
that you know decent person control
continous delivery practices kind of
agile practices um you know smallish
teams and so on and so on like this
stuff has been as you know like known
and practiced for you decades not in
every organization but in in many
organizations if I understand correctly
it's like all these principles and
practices are the fundamental things
more than the things that sometimes
teams tend to focus on like the team
types and the interaction modes am I
correct in stating this sort of yes I
mean in the sense that team topologies
is but we we'll get we'll dive into the
the details in a minute but teens
polities came out of all of the
practices and awareness around the
devops movement that started back in
about 2008 which was sparked really by
the availab ability of kind of
infrastructure automation configuration
Automation and Cloud that would kind of
emerged around about you know 2006 2007
2008 so suddenly there was new practices
available suddenly it infrastructure was
no longer the bottleneck and suddenly we
had this coalescing of practices like
continuous delivery which the book came
out in 2010 newer tooling that allowed
us to do for example application logging
at scale with quite High Fidelity and so
on and so on a bunch of tooling came out
in this kind of space which which
suddenly gave technologists way better
um much greater variety of options for
going quickly so anyway the one way of
looking at te polities is really it's an
opinionated expression of core devops
principles when devops is really the
original meaning of of the word devops
which is like effective development and
operations teams working together not
just a very shrunken version of devops
which some people refer to which is just
like a kind of dealing with build and
deployment pipelines or dealing with
like cuberes infrastructure or whatever
that version which is what devops tends
to be these days but back in you know 10
years ago what have you it really meant
this whole approach to getting it
delivery working really really
effectively so it came out of all that
stuff so teties at one level is really
just a natural expression of what you
would get if you put a few constraints
in place we need to have fast flow we
need to think about cognitive load we
need to have a team based approach we
need teams to be small so we've got high
trust and can go quickly we think about
Conway's law we need to have a language
for navigating this stuff we need to
make sure that we're detecting
opportunities for improvement across the
organization on a regular basis rather
just having lots of small teams or Silo
and so on and so on if you take all of
those constraints and apply them in the
context of sort of modern like software
and it delivery you will get something
like Teen topologies out like it's a
natural em it's not just coming out of
nowhere it's a natural consequence of
having these kind of operating
constraints in place so we weren't just
like inventing a whole lot of stuff this
is like the techniques in that we talk
about in Te had already been used by
some companies for like 10 years
effectively but we put particular
terminology we put particular spin on it
if you like or we put a particular
opinionated view of what was kind of
already happening in the industry based
on some companies the more advanced
companies like Netflix and some of the
teams in Amazon AWS and a few other
places like this some of them are in the
book and we said look let's try and
reverse engineer what's going on here
like why did Amazon talk about two Pizza
teams what's going on it sounds funny
right two Peters ha blah blah blah
what's highest Pizza is it is it an
Italian pizza or is it American Pizza
all that stuff right but clearly
underneath there is something really
important and the thing that was that
that we reverse engineered effectively
underneath that two- piece of team thing
was the trust that you get from a team
that is relatively small and therefore
you can go really quickly and you can
have autonomy combine that with the
really important design principle from
Jeff beos back in I think it was even
2001 or two or something where he said
like something like every interface must
be be externalizable so in other words
every kind of API or or thing that you
build you need to treat as if you're
going to expose it to the internet
effectively expose it to external
customers because that makes for an
incredibly powerful scaling technique
for systems and for the organization
itself and so we took things like that
and tried to recast it in language that
was kind of independent of any one
particular organization and put it into
a form that was suitable for kind of a
typical organizations that we'd come
across typical Banks typical retailers
typical logistics companies typical
pharmaceutical companies typical you
know any kind of company basically
manufacturer whatever typical government
department and so on and so on we tried
to find language that was accessible
approachable we tried to come up with
patterns and terminology and diagramming
style in particular the diagram style
was really important is really important
for us we tried to pull together these
things in a way which is accessible to
technologists and to non- technologists
one of the things that I've been doing
in in my career for a long long time is
bridging the Gap often it's a it's a
Chasm between technology and people
outside of Technology explaining how
this stuff works and why and that's
definitely one of the things that we've
seen with the teen book is people who
are non- technologists they might be
head of strategy they might be CEO they
might be Co who can read the book and go
I get this it's explained in a way which
is not condescending doesn't require me
to understand too much about technology
and so on and so on can I ask you now a
question because before when you said
that with te topologies you try to you
said desynchronize te am I using the
correct term I think you said
desynchronize instead of synchronizing
and now I find this intriguing it's like
what do you mean with that with the
synchronizing maybe can you give us also
a real life example from some project
you worked on yes so there is a kind of
Common Sense there's a like a natural
tendency for organizations I think
people and organizations as a whole to
want to try and synchronize the work of
multiple teams for some reason there's a
belief that the synchronization of that
work is needed in order to get the right
value out at the right time and so on
and so on the problem is synchronization
doesn't scale and the more
synchronization you do the worse the
problem gets and we see this in in large
organizations where they they've got big
programs of work and you've got hundreds
of teams all like kind of working on
something and the amount of effort that
goes into synchronizing that work
bringing it all together integrating it
planning and trying to get this thing
built in time for this other team to use
and then that team's waiting on another
team and so on and so on if you actually
do the calculation on this the amount of
money that organizations are spending
just having teams waiting on each other
is millions and millions and millions of
dollars every year it's absolute Madness
and yet it's the kind of so-called
common sense it's not actually good
sense it's just a sense that that is
there is accepted wisdom if you like
turns out there's another way to do it
and the other way to do it is to
deliberately desynchronize so keep
things like have a limit on the number
of teams or the number number of people
in a kind of synchronization unit if you
like and keep that extremely small so
maybe you limit the synchronization to
just two or three teams that's what's
that that's like it might be eight or or
15 or like 24 people and say okay we can
try and synchronize between a couple or
maybe three teams but much bigger than
that let's deliberately desynchronize it
let's deliberately not try and bring
that together and use modern techniques
like feature flags and a bunch of other
things so that we'll deliver something
into life first then at some point later
something else will pop into live and
then maybe a couple of weeks later
something else will arrive in the live
environment and then we get the value
but by deliberately desynchronizing and
using these kind of techniques we
actually get the value sooner because
that value will appear in production
sooner than if we try to synchronize it
all together can you give us now maybe
briefly a real life example from a
particular system or project you worked
on you know to help our listeners create
some mental models of how things may may
work in practice you know brief you
don't need to describe the entire
project
this is how Netflix has run for decades
effectively this is how the entire of
Amazon AWS runs Amazon AWS you're not
actually permitted to like insist that
another team changes their API within a
given time frame that's how they've
managed to scale so big in fact if you
look at the way that Amazon a scales
when they add a new employee they get
more than one employees worth of value
out of that new person effectively
because of how the scaling Works whereas
most organizations when they add a new
person they get about 085 or even less
worth of employee value out of that
person because most organizations are
not operating on the same scaling laws
so the best examples are already there
from organizations doing this kind of
thing they're huge and they're
delivering huge amounts of value but it
seems mysterious mysterious to be
organizations outside of that way of
working because it's so counterintuitive
what kind of organizations you know
these team topologies approach is
suitable for you know startups small
projects big projects involving how many
teams you know is that a sweet spot and
are there any situations where you would
actually recommend something else it's a
great question so I think the sweet spot
is is actually quite a large spot if you
like but it's crucially for
organizations that genuinely want to
empower their people want genuinely want
to empower teams genuinely want to make
the organization a more Humane and
effective place and it's not a good fit
for organizations or for leaders that
actually want to exert strong control
command and control kind of ways of
working so if you do command and control
then do command and control tell people
what to do accept that your organization
is going to be very slow accept that
it's going to be very annoying and
painful and people are going to want to
leave and accept that the organization
will probably fail at some point if
that's what you want to do then go for
that but if you genuinely want to have
like an organization that's actually
effective and Humane and Nimble and has
outsized performance and gets way more
value out of the employees than the
competitors then approaches like te
parties are actually extremely good fit
and so does it work also say in small
startups you know startups that have
let's say 5 10 people in total because
they are just starting does it work also
in these very small scale kind of
projects if you've got very small number
of people then you probably don't see
really the effects of Conway's law and
the effects of some of the scaling
effects that you would get outside at
larger organizational sizes so if you've
only got say 10 people you could
probably get away with just kind of not
really defining the boundaries so
strongly because you're still exploring
kind of what you're doing and what the
market fit is and so on and so on but as
you head towards I don't know maybe 15
people you probably need to start
thinking about where to put some
boundaries for cognitive load boundaries
for flow boundaries for scaling this
kind of thing because if you don't then
you you're in danger of growing the
thing too big and then it becomes
actually too difficult to manage so we
did some work
long time ago back in
2015 with a startup in video advertising
so you might not believe it but back
then this is based in the UK back then
sorry not video advertising it was TV
advertising television advertising so
National broadcast in in in the UK and
back then adverts for broadcast
television were produced recorded they
were burned onto a DVD and they were put
on a courier a motorcycle Courier and
moved from one side of London to the
other and that was the quickest way to
do the delivery and that's what the
startup was trying to address and
successfully did it was bought by I
can't remember a VC or something later
and so what they did is to do all this
via Amazon AWS in the cloud back then
2015 or something they're the first
solution to like cloud-based advertising
review and approval for the world I
think certainly for the UK market and we
were helping them when they were around
about kind of 15 people and we saw some
early problem starting to arise is
because they weren't really thinking
about cognitive load they weren't really
thinking about kind of skills
differentiation and so on and so on or
or we help them to think about it
effectively we help them to think so
well look you're getting to the point
where there's actually too much to think
about for this one group of people you
need to differentiate the skills a bit
and maybe start to think about providing
what we end up calling a platform and
maybe start to think about something
that's a bit more complicated so like
take away the cognitive load for that
complicated thing to a smaller group of
people so that other people can focus on
the the end custom experience and so on
and so on so like we started to test out
some of the te's ideas early on but we
started to see these problems emerge as
I said when there was around about 15 to
20 people in the startup are there any
kind of things where actually te
topologies is not necessarily applicable
you know I'm talking about situations
where there is you know a small team
trying to discover something in a domain
you know fleshing out information they
are not quite sure about what they're
doing so there is a lot of
experimentation prototyping discovery
or maybe in some companies now and there
is a lot of data there are data
analytics teams and that are not
necessarily featured well feature teams
or stream stream align teams so or
complicated subsisten basically what
they mean is are there types of teams
that actually are a bit outside the team
topologies framework but then they need
to interact with teams within that
framework great question so we thought
that maybe R&D research and development
was one area where some of the apologies
approaches might not work but we were
told that we were wrong we were told we
were wrong by the global head of an R&D
Division and a big global global
pharmaceutical company and he was like
no no no these definitely apply these
definitely apply on R&D so we're like
okay fine we'll take your word for it so
if you think about it if we're doing
exploration if we're doing analytics if
we're you working on a product or a
service or a user Journey or something
like this with software or with where
we're enabled by software we've got a
core Mission or ideally we've got a core
Mission we understand who are delivering
that value too we've got a value
consumer effectively of the work that
we're doing and there's an amount of
stuff that gets in the way of that value
delivery and so we've got a sense of a
stream of value a value stream it's
sometimes easier to feel like it's a
stream of value but even with research
and development even with kind of
Discovery and you know noodling around
and experimentation there's still a
sense in which we we've got a value
stream because the value is in the
lessons that we're learning and we're
delivering that value to you know some
sort of stakeholder who's paying for
that work to be done and for those
discoveries to happen there's always an
amount of stuff which is a distraction
there's a amount of stuff which causes
effectively friction around that work
and we'll always hit some snags which
relate to areas of expertise that we
just don't have in the team and that's
why the team supportting approach Works
across all knowledge work effectively
this is what we've discovered we didn't
design it that way but actually what we
ended up doing when we writing the book
and thinking through the patterns is
providing a framework or an approach to
knowledge work to navigating knowledge
work technology assisted knowledge work
I should say so te body is really an
approach to highly effective technology
assisted knowledge work at PACE at speed
so maybe you can give us more details
about these structures you know the team
structures Communications among them so
team is we start with to be honest we
start with a massive assumption I've
mentioned it already and this massive
assumption is that the organization
understands its value streams and this
is this turns out to be basically mostly
not true most organizations need a lot
of help in understanding their value
streams which is fine we're here to help
the teams I've built over the last few
years are super impressive and we've
been doing lots of interesting work with
lots of organizations so let's say we
get to the point where we start to
understand some of the value streams at
least perhap we're doing a pilot project
and and we've got I don't know five or
six teams involved so we start with this
idea of here's a stream of value we want
to have the the fastest flow of value
inside the value stream in order to do
that we do not want any handoffs from
one team to another we can't possibly
have one team that does a bit of work
and then hands off to another team that
does a bit more work and then hands off
to another team because if if You'
studied anything around queuing Theory
and stuff like that on process control
then handoffs absolutely kill flow so
like how do we get to the point where
we've got end to end value flow for that
particular like part of the value stream
we need to have a team that owns the end
to end thing we can't have a hand off
from one team to another so that's our
starting point and that's what we call a
stream aligned team they're aligned to
the stream of value we deliberately
chose a word there that is not too
opinionated it's a little bit kind of
neutral that's why it's called stream
aligned team it's just aligned to the
stream of value it's not a product team
it's not a feature team it's not
anything else like this because those
words mean all kind of different things
in different places and crucially stream
aligned team it's into the stream of
value that works in all kinds of
knowledge work as well which is very
convenient so that's the starting point
and the team in this case is about up to
about eight people now for most
organizations that's very small it's a
very small number of people in that
group interestingly I was talking to
someone at a conference in Hamburg last
week and he said Matthew like eight or
nine people is a huge team for me I get
by with three or four people anyway so
he's he's in a he's in a world where
he's really used to really really small
teams but anyway up to about eight
people is is because that number of
people we still get a very high degree
of trust but we've got quite a broad
range of skills so inside a team like
that we've got a mixture of different
skills sometimes it's called cross
functional sometimes it's called
multifunctional multi-skilled we
deliberately bring in different
perspectives so that we can go very
quickly sometimes inside a team like
that we might have like an expert or a
compliance Specialist or like a legal
even a lawyer inside a team like that
maybe if we need to go very very very
quickly and understand the the context
for for making decisions and for
building these services and running
these services so that team's got
everything it needs to deliver value
independently 90% of the time that's our
starting point so and ideally we'd have
multiple independent streams of value
with these stream aliance teams multiple
streamline teams if we could get away
with having a 100 streamline teams in
the organization providing 100 different
value flows that would be where we start
like if we could get away with that then
that would be brilliant but in reality
the reality is a bit more messy in
reality if you take one of those or
several of these you know stream lines
teams if they're fully independent then
over time they are dealing with more and
more and more and more things they're
dealing with data they're dealing with
security they're dealing with generative
AI they're dealing with infrastructure
they're dealing with reporting audits a
whole bunch of stuff like this and over
time those extra things don't really
relate to their core mission if their
core mission is focused on applying for
a credit card or ordering a pizza or
doing a specific kind of drug Discovery
or you know whatever whatever the
mission of that team is whatever the
value that they're supposed to be
delivering is all these extra things
then start to slow them down effectively
they start to be a distraction they
start to eat into the the cognitive
capacity of the collective team and so
we need some approaches that help to
encourage an ongoing fast flow value in
that streamlines team how can we do that
well one way is by dealing with some of
those aspects like security audit
compliance whatever that are not really
related to the core Mission how can we
do that there's multiple different ways
and there's three different types of
team that we talk about in the team
part's book that help with that so the
second team type is called enabling team
enabling team is a team of experts that
can help to uplift the capability in the
streamlined team so these might be
experts in legal compliance or bio
Sciences research or or credit card data
regulations or something and that team
of experts can come in and help the
streamlined team for a small period of
time maybe a few days a few weeks until
the streamlined team's capability is
uplifted until the Streamline team
understands how to deal with that aspect
better and they can then bake that into
their everyday processes the enabling
team helps the stream align team to
acquire skills they don't have exactly
that's one of the things they do exactly
that's one of the things they do the
enabling team might also though because
the enabling team might also detect that
you know 17 out of 20 teams all have the
same problem they all find this
particular piece of technology very
difficult or this particular aspect of
Regulation very difficult to work with
because they're working across multiple
different stream Alliance teams in the
organization so they the enabling team
acts like a boundary spanner in
organizational design terminology
they're detecting this stuff they're
acting like a sensing mechanism across
the organization and then they can go H
if 17 out of 20 teams are all having the
same problem maybe we need to do
something about it so then they can say
you we've we've detected the fact that
there's an opportunity for enhancing
that capability across the organization
not just sort of solving the same
problem time and time again what do we
do well we can do whole organization
training we can uh buy a new tool we can
maybe hire some people and put them into
every team if we need to we don't have
to but that could be one option or maybe
we build or enhance the experience of
using that particular technology or that
particular thing how can we build it
well we'll that's where the the other
two types of Team come in one of which
is called a complicated subsystem team
where we're taking a very specific part
of the work inside streamlined teams
which is really complicated it might be
like an algorithmic thing like a video
processing algorithm it might be data
preparation for generative AI it might
be something that's that's just not
realistic to expect people in the
streamlines team to be able to take that
kind of um that mental load and we take
it out into a complicated subsystem team
but the reason we take it out into that
separate team is because we're dealing
with the cognitive load to enable the
Streamline team to go more quickly how
do you decide you know to create this
kind of complicated subsystem team so
what are the signals in a stream align
team that they need this kind of help
that's a good question so the signals
are that stream Aline team is basically
just struggling with that particular
specific aspect of technology that
specific library or component or
algorithm or concept or whatever and
we've tried to uplift their skills using
an enabling team and that just hasn't
worked it's just way like the enabling
team really can't provide the uplift
that's needed we've sent them on
training still the Streamline team is
just saying look this is just way too
complicated you need you need people
who' have got phds or or like a research
background in physics or astrophysics or
Nuclear Physics or something you need to
get these kind of people involved in
here who really understand the the
complicated mathematics and so then we
can go oh okay it's one of those things
let's break it out as a separate have
you got an example you know from a real
situation you have been involved in this
you know to make this kind of decision
well yeah so that video processing the
TV advert startup I talked about before
there's one particular part of their
system that was video
encoding and they didn't actually write
the algorithm but it was a software
itself that was running on a particular
kind of operating system and so on and
so on it was quite awkward to manage and
it was out of the experience of most
people in the team to work with and so
actually made much more sense to kind of
hide the details of that inside what we
now call a complicated subsystem to
enable the the other people to focus on
the user experience better and by doing
that it actually got better flow they
could have better pretention to detail
to the experience of the the approval
process for the adverts rather than
having to think about the details of
configuring and running and operating
this what was effectively a complicated
subsystem for for video and coding and
and decoding so all this seems to be
also revolving around the cognitive load
con cep kind of you know people that
have to know things and they don't
necessarily know everything so you
mentioned cognitive load already a few
times so quite a central Concept in the
team topologies but how do we Define
that in a let's say relatively accurate
way so what is it when we talk because
intuitively it seems to be you know lots
of stuff things that make us tired to
think about I don't know but how do we
Define this it's a good point so in the
teage book we we use a definition from
Australian psychologist John sweller who
defined it in the 19 in 1988 I think
it's fair to say there's some debate
about around the sort of the
applicability and validity of of the
John sweller view of cognitive load
there's different ways of interpreting
it and in fact we've we've been working
with dror Laura Vice who has got PhD in
organizational psychology and she's been
helping us to sort of come up with a
more rounded approach to cognitive load
which takes into account a bunch of
other extra kind of Dimensions around
the workplace around around the
additional distractions that people have
got in the workplace and so on and so on
and so on and that's been encoded into a
tool that is now out of beta so it's
actually available for for General
release called temperature a bit like
temperature but we're taking the
temperature of the team so the kind of
team prer you go to team.com you'll find
that and we we've run that successfully
with a bank in Europe and with telecoms
provider in Europe as well and they've
been running with that for the best part
of a year I believe it's my colleague
Manuel P who who who runs that side of
things but we've been working with them
very closely and it's had some really
really useful results in terms of
looking for detecting High cognitive
load detecting the change in cognitive
load over time because it might change
depending on kind of the time of year if
you've got like Black Friday sales and
stuff like this for a for a retailer
then you know the cognitive load
probably goes up because there's a load
of other things to think about and so on
and so on so we're exploring that very
much at the moment and in the second
major te's book which we've started
planning now we will have an updated
kind of expression or updated view of
our intent around cognitive load that
came out in the first book I think our
intent was absolutely sound like to to
really think about the human kind of
what what it's like to be human in
knowledge work I think the intent to
bring that in and to be realistic about
that was really important because to be
honest like if we're overloading people
they can't possibly do good work they
can't possibly look after these systems
in an effective way it's just it doesn't
make any sense so let's let's be
realistic about it clearly we can use
technology to take away some of that
extraneous cognitive load some of the
some of the cognitive load which just
isn't very interesting cool let's use
gen let's use cloud let's use whatever
Technologies to to help with that cool
but that just means that those human
beings can now focus on something that's
more Mission Centric which is great
which is where you want to be and
there's that cycle always kind of is
always changing because technolog is
always changing but we're always trying
to get into a position where we're
balancing the amount of cognitive load
with fast flow with the amount of flow
if we squeeze down the cognitive load
too much if we just give people a tiny
amount of things to do the slice is
probably too thin we're probably not
getting enough value if we expand the
value stack if you like or the amount of
cognitive load too much then people have
probably slowed down so there's always a
constant tension between cognitive load
and fast flow which is nice because it
gets interesting then how do you get the
right balance there you know how do you
measure cognitive load to decide what
the right balance is how do you do that
well so the the team pature tool is our
offering for how to how to measure
cognitive load and it includes lots of
different variables basically and it
needs to be done on an ongoing basis
effectively I think there's probably
going to em where we already starting to
see emerging some tools that uh sort of
automatically detect aspects of
cognitive load not everything but
aspects of it by looking at messages in
slack for example or chat by looking at
things like cyclomatic complexity or
other measures of code complexity and
things like this and mapping that to
teams so there's tools like code scene
that get involved in that which is
amazing and other kind of tools like
this which are which are using kind of
telemetry and organizational signals to
give us some Clues into where cognitive
load might be higher than others and
that just helps us pinpoint and and
start an investigation okay that's
interesting so it's a kind of looking at
various aspects both technical in the
code base the shape and non- Technical
in terms of the people interaction what
they say say on messages on slack and
the things they talk about and things
they may be struggling with and somehow
come up with a measure to decide this
team actually needs help there's tooling
ways of doing and we're actually working
with an interesting startup that's in
this space that is using Genna to do
sentiment analysis at scale and we're
working with them to see how we can
incorporate that into our Consulting
offering but it's a signal the tools is
one important part of it but we also
need to focus on the psychological
safety and the culture of the
organization that enables people to
speak up because if people are afraid no
amount of tooling is really going to
help we need to be getting into position
where people are empowered and feel safe
enough to be able to say look this thing
over here just is a nightmare we can't
work with it at all we need to have a
conversation about this we need to
improve the user experience of working
with this thing over here they need to
know they're not going to get shouted
down for for raising that that's why I
said before that like teens p is
definitely suitable for organizations
that that truly want to empower people
but is not suitable for situations where
you where the the leaders or the whoever
managers execs really want to imp poose
Commander control definitely say that it
needs
these kind of generative approaches to
running organizations need fundamentally
start with you know Foundation of
psychological safety to enable people to
actually operate well we should probably
mention the fourth type of team that
that's in the book in the book we
actually called it a platform team is
actually wrong that's the only mistake
in the book really that's the only
coming out with anata of the book to
correct that we might do we might do it
should really say platform group
because it's not a separate team type Ah
that's interesting so can you expand on
this what do you mean with this in our
world a team is a group of up to about
eight people so very high trust and
multiple different skills and so on
whereas the platform concept is actually
more like a grouping of teams we expect
to see inside a platform inside a kind
of platform boundary we expect to see
multiple different types of teams in in
a large organization I mean if it's a
tiny organization of 15 20 people then
you might have just a single platform
team but as soon as you get to Beyond I
don't know 30 people then you're going
to have multiple different teams that
operate inside a given like platform
let's see if I understand this correctly
so it's like we can think about some
team that is dealing with maybe creating
some I don't know abstractions on top of
some AWS things I don't know configure
databases in a specific way so when the
teams need that they have everything
done for them but then we can think
about I don't know security team people
that are expert in security aspects and
do some other stuff that requires a
different still platform level but a
different kind of special skill and
things along these lines or am I missing
so yes but to be honest a lot of
organizations talk about a lot of it
departments and things that have you
seen polities talk about like a cloud
platform which is great so that group
provides kind of abstractions and
simplifications around the use of cloud
typical inside most Enterprises you've
got multiple different Cloud providers
just have technology providers you need
some kind of simplification and
abstractions around it but inside there
you've got multiple different teams
working on different things what are the
value streams what the value consumers
for the different things you're working
on it's not just about a blob of
Technology like if you basically need to
look at the value that that group of
people is providing and to whom are we
providing it we're providing it to other
internal teams okay great understand
their needs what's the user experience
or sometimes called developer experience
what's the road map how does it all work
together how are you going to work out
what comes next it's just product
management I don't know if it is correct
but sounds like you know it's stream
align teams all the way down since a
kind of pattern there also the platform
grouping is actually some stream align
teams where the customers in this case
and that use that need the value
delivered are actually the stream align
teams that provide value to the end
customers exactly exactly it's like it's
like the famous Terry practic quotation
right Turtles all the way down yeah
seems to be similar to that you it's
either streamline teams all the way down
or or you might argue it's platforms or
platform groupings all the way down
because underneath that internal
platform grouping there's really
there'll be a platform which is like a
cloud provider or some other kind of
Technology provider and it's the same
pattern inside there obviously if you
zoom into AWS or Google or Microsoft
guess what you see some teams that are
focused on particular streams of value
call them streamline teams and they were
they're busy working on some stuff too
it keeps going all the way down all the
way down to the operating system you've
got different teams working on different
aspects of you know Red Hat Linux or or
Windows or whatever it is and so on and
so on and same all the way down to the
embedded software you've got different
teams working on different streams of
value inside there so it's a very
fractal approach fractal self-similar
approach you can zoom in zoom out which
is really good because you can it fits
very well with wly mapping like
strategic awareness and approaches like
core domain charts and kind of domain
room design because you got nice bounded
contexts from DDD so we can apply the
bounded context like inside a platform
grouping but then we don't always want
to think about all of those contexts so
we can zoom out and just think about
contexts which sit outside of that
platform grouping so it really helps
with navigating all the way across the
the whole organization because we can
use these techniques the same techniques
we can use across the entire knowledge
work organization I see and one last
question before we start talking about
you know how to get started with Team
topology say if in an organization
people want to implement them how they
should start but before that now with
team topologies and you mentioned this
also today there is an emphasis on Fast
flow yeah which I would say that looks
like productivity in a sense but how
does that affect you know other
qualities of the system you know quality
of the code and performances anything
else I mean is this fast flow going to
happen at the expense of other system
qualities or maybe not let me relate a
story so it's possible to take the fast
flow thing to the extreme and to over
index to really focus on just individual
fast flow of of value inside little
teams or little departments without that
stuff being coordinated but crucially
without it being related to each other
we actually did some work with an
organization a few years ago where they
were they actually pretty good knowing
what their value streams were and their
customers were and they had Platforms in
place they had enabling teams in place
based on team apologies and so on or or
influenced by it but they had some
strange incentives and this was about I
don't know what why why these things
were in place but anyway you had like a
development manager saying to their team
don't talk to people from the other team
next to you don't talk to people from
that team over there your time is my
time like it's precious I want you to
focus on just this product and so they
ended up with his Madness like his
complete Madness they had like
effectively they had like whatever it
was 70 teams but they were completely
independent they're acting like many
agencies like many like digital agencies
like 80 digital agencies inside the
organization but like they weren't
talking to each other they weren't
sharing anything and so on and so on
that was an example of this kind of
approach taken in a direction that we
kind of didn't expect and and would
never recommend and actually that
approach kind of is reflected in some of
the criticism of teen polities that
we've seen over the last five years
people saying that this leads to
fragmented value and blah blah blah and
yes of course like if if you take this
to the extreme and don't think about the
organizational culture and learning
aspects and a bunch of these things then
of course you're going to end up with
something that looks very strange okay
before going to the implementing team
topologies just I want to see if I
understand something because you know at
the beginning when I ask about the team
types and communication interaction
modes you said well it's not a good
point to start because this seems to be
where everybody focuses and then he went
to the principle so is what you said now
one of the reasons why you don't want to
start with the particular elements of
Team structures and interaction modes
and instead emphasize the principles is
just to help people avoid focusing too
much say on the mechanics without really
understanding what the underlying
reasons are exactly the team types look
really easy we'll just copy pce them
without thinking about the reasons for
that and the reasons are really
important like the reasons why we why we
create a platform grouping or the
reasons why we create uh complicated sub
system team and so on all that stuff is
is driven by flow and cognitive loan
it's driven in a very specific way and
and it's not just we've seen examples
where the HR department or the people
department has like has designed the
organization using these kind of teams
without any awareness of like cognitive
load or flow or sense of value streams
and and that's you know at best it's
misinformed and at worst it's actually
counterproductive for the organization
because you've got the boundaries in the
wrong place okay now let's talk about
you know how to get started with this
let's say we have an organization that
they want to let's say improve their
team structures and the way they liiver
value and they look into team topologies
yeah how should they get started because
I see also in the book itself you state
that organizations at different stages
of Technical and cultural maturity will
find different team structures to be
effective yeah so how an organization
should get started maybe you can also
tell us how they can find where they
stand with the respect to organizational
maturity in for that so there's a nice
phrase that John smart from sooner
safeer happier uses so soon safe happier
is the book that came out I think the
year after teen 4S by the same publisher
it Revolution by the way which is an
amazing publishing house and it's great
to be part of that family pretty much
any book from it evolution is something
that that I buy personally and read and
I basically recommend everyone else to
do as well so John smart from soon safe
happier he talks about elephant
Carpaccio so how do you eat an elephant
you slice it very very
thinly and so the way you would start in
any of these approaches with we're
talking about endtoend value delivery so
where we start is we find an endtoend
stream of value that we can work with
straight away basically that's our
starting point so it might be called a
pilot project it might be called
hopefully not the word project but pilot
we're going to Pilot this with one
particular area so for example we're
doing some work in a European bank at
the moment it's one of the smaller
European Banks which is actually quite
convenient because it's easier to get
things done they're not so huge and
let's say there is opportunity to
differentiate that bank's offering in
the marketplace by making it really
really easy not just easy but like a
really good experience to apply for a
loan or apply for a mortgage something
like this and we say okay well that's
actually quite a useful kind of endtoend
sort of value stream there's going to be
ongoing differentiation ongoing work to
improve this experience over the next 18
months yeah maybe longer right so
actually we've got Clear customer for
the value which is the person that we're
who wants the loan we understand their
needs well or we can do the work to
understand their needs and what what
what we need from them and we can pull
together like a streamlines team let's
say it's eight people that can work on
this thing that's where we'll start
anyway maybe eventually it's a couple of
teams or three teams or something but to
start with let's assume it's just one
team what would it take just to need one
team of eight people we'll use
particular technologies that are easier
to work with so that we can just keep it
to a single team so we might use low
code or we might use particular
languages that that that are more amable
to like really focus on on Innovation
around that applying for a loan use a
journey and then we say okay that's fine
what about things like security Cloud
infrastructure data a bunch of other
things what's the minimum we need in
place to enable that streamline team to
do its job let's work it out let's work
backwards from having that team in place
what else are they going to need what
else well we could explore it over time
but as they working on these things as
they get their deployment pipelines in
place as they get their Cloud
infrastructure in place we're looking to
see what's slowing them down what's
taking their time away from that
endtoend value delivery which is focused
on applying for a loan we say okay it
looks like this aspect of cloud
infrastructure is causing a problem this
is really slowing things down can we
find a sensible boundary and provide
some of those things as a service from
what we're going to call a platform or
platform grouping in team polities
terminology so we're only putting in
these other constructs to support that
flow of value by reducing cognitive load
and we're using that pilot to explore
the language we're using to explore the
different team types to explore the
different Dynamics when we bring in an
enabling team when we when the enabling
team disengages and goes off somewhere
else explore or how we talk about the
value that we're getting how we talk
about the experience of working in that
way how we do showcasing how we do a
whole bunch of other things like this
and we use that pilot to learn how we're
going to do this and what kind of things
we need and what kind of what what's the
experience like and and so on and so on
and then we find another opportunity to
do it maybe this time it's not applying
for a loan maybe this time it's
something different really you go one
thing at that time and somehow you you
defend the slices of your elephant
caracho in this way exactly so over time
build up more and more slices of
elephant basically thin slices learning
as we go and deliberately sharing that
learning across the organization and
over time creating a bit of friendly
fomo friendly fear of missing out like
like engagement basically it's not about
the fear but it's about like oh that's
really looks really cool I want to be
involved with that what would it take
and building the momentum and excitement
over time but crucially making sure we
learn a bit of PR to interest the others
to into the approach curiosity yeah
curiosity curiosity around missing out
what's that Curiosity around it's that
kind of thing we want people to be
curious and interested in what's going
on and try and see the value but
crucially like getting to that end to
state from the very beginning I did some
work in the UK government a few years
ago and there had been some suppliers
working in there for multiple years and
they still hadn't deployed anything to
production they'd already been working
there for I think it's was three or four
years not a single line of code have
been deployed to production in that time
that's the place where it needs to start
on day one you build your deployment
pipel plan it goes into production you
deploy a text file and you say okay
let's work backwards let's get audit
Trail in place let get the logging in
place let's get the approval gates in
place that enable that stuff to happen
even though it's just a text file
because once we've got all of that trust
and awareness about how we're going to
do this then we can go really really
quickly I can imagine those situations
like you've being the teams working 3
four years without deploying anything
then you go there and deploy something
whatever it is the motivation starts to
increase because it's oh finally we are
actually achieving something but we try
and do that from day one like absolutely
like we we do what's necessary I mean
that's that's part of what my companies
do we do the work with real people and
talk people through it to get to the
point where we can have that elephant
patcha because we've done the kind of
trailblazing we've solved the hard
problems around technology deployment
pipelines approval Gates authorization
security compliance all of that kind of
stuff to enable us to get endtoend
deployment from day one and then over
time we're going to build up what the
application does and yes like we might
deliberately like effectively hide the
application from the outside world but
we're doing the full end to end
deployment from from as close to day one
as possible ideally from day one and
working in that way then becomes so eye
openening for the stakeholders because
they can say wow the speed of delivery
here is just incredible we've managed to
get this thing out of there and it's
compliant and it's we've got an audit
Trail for it the auditor is happy with
it and why do we not work this way with
everything are there any common
challenges or pitfalls that team
encounter when implementing a team
topologies approach things that you see
again and again you know frequent
problems first of all if you think about
teach is basically an opinionated
version of what the industry is
collective wisdom around devops and
cloud and these practices it's an
extension of the original agile software
delivery but clearly like when the
original agile Manifesto was created
there was nothing like cloud like you
couldn't deliver to a global audience on
a multiple times a day basis that just
wasn't a thing like the original
Manifesto was all around desktop
software and and so on and so on so
although agile practices are are
essential they're not enough if you like
for for modern software
so yeah so at one level like teen is not
necessarily a special thing it's not
different from sort of collective wisdom
around the industry over the last kind
of 20 years really it's an opinionated
version of that so part of my answer is
really around what are the ways in which
organizations fail to apply Collective
wisdom around engineer software
engineering and so it's quite common and
that's the same everywhere right it's
they they organizations don't don't take
the time to understand what's going on
underneath they don't understand what
really like even if you just at like the
original agile practices I don't really
understand the what's really going on in
terms of some of the team practices
things what's really going on in like
Ensemble programming what's really going
on in terms of retrospective and things
like that some of these things just
become ceremonies that then lose all of
their like underlying meaning because
the organization has kind of hasn't
taken the time to embed that true
awareness of the value and so that so
that they they end up becoming sort of
meaningless that's one of the things
that we've seen with te polities we've
seen organization
take a very thin or very shallow
understanding of team polities they just
look at four team types and and some
interaction modes they don't really
understand the interaction modes we've
not talked about them today but they
still go oh I don't really understand
that stuff it's not about structure they
see 14 types and then they just go well
that's it basically three weeks we'll be
done and we literally were were on a
workshop with a retailer in North
America the CEO had read the book and in
the middle of the workshop he was like
okay this sounds great we'll be done in
three weeks then we all left and then
there was this like really awkward pause
when we realized that he actually meant
it because he really just thought it was
about renaming a few teams then we done
he hadn't internalized like the massive
changes where that it implies the
typical thing I want to change
everything without really changing
anything of without anything exactly
because the implication team apologies
the implication of fast flow in general
I mean the implication of like original
agile really but anyway is we're
reorienting everything to Value stream
approaches and that includes the
architecture that includes the funding
that includes the processes that
includes if you're working in a big
organization that includes the external
procurement the procurement boundaries
you're using when you're procuring
software from external suppliers need to
be flow align if you don't do that then
then you don't have any flow so like
there's a huge implication if you want a
flow-based way of working which is like
super effective and super Humane if you
get there you've got to change quite a
lot so you have to change lots of things
not simply the names of the teams or Nam
of teams we should have put a health
warning we should have put a warning on
the team book which said warning the
implications of working this way are way
bigger than you probably imagine you've
got an opportunity because you said they
working on the next book about it put
actually you should do that maybe in the
cover yeah one last question about
implementation so te topologies are not
supposed to be static like the
organization evolves they need evolve
maybe you know the value evolves there
could be changes of Direction so how can
an organization keep the teams aligned
with the changes of value streams and
flow so how can an organization do that
there's some really nice techniques in
particular there's a dynamic ring from
Heidi hend which provides like patterns
for reshaping and changing the
composition of teams in a way that keeps
the teams healthy so you're not just
pulling people out of teams and throwing
them into another team or like cutting a
team off after a few weeks or a few
months there's a way of changing teams
which is way more healthy than most
organizations of practice that's pretty
useful I would imagine that these
practices have an element that is some
kind of incremental and maybe iterative
you're are not going to say okay guys
from now on this is the new shape of the
organization it's like you know a sudden
change from one day to another imagine
that is something that you can do in
steps somehow exactly and that's exactly
what the team interaction modes are
there to help Define so like
collaboration and exess of service and
facilitation the interaction modes
effectively set expectations about what
it feels like to work with another team
or another set of teams so we're leaning
on the emotional aspect of of people in
the organization saying well setting
those kind of expectations and then
allowing people to detect when actually
to be honest it feels like you know
we're expecting to just consume this
thing as a service from an API but
actually we're having to email or or or
message people all the time about this
thing it doesn't feel very service likee
use it as a signal to say okay the
service boundary used to be good now
it's not yeah I see so any kind of
friction that is kind of not normal for
some probably it's difficult to Define
it very precisely but something that
they look that are more Awkward than
what they should be are signals it's a
signal for us to have a conversation
like it's a placeholder guess what it's
like a placeholder for a conversation
right it's that kind of mentality we're
looking for things that tell us let's
regroup let's rethink this thing no
one's blaming anyone the the boundary we
put in place 18 months ago was was good
at the time the technolog moved on the
domains moved on the regulations moved
on we need to shift where responsibility
lies so that we got sensible amount of
cognitive load and we've got better flow
let's just have a conversation okay
let's have a conversation like no one's
it gets out of that kind of Blame Game
blame trap yeah yeah okay okay well
thank you very much I think we now are
approaching the end of our conversation
so I think he helped us you know to do
actually quite a great job I think of
introducing team topologies I think our
listeners will have a let's say a better
introduction
lots of things to think about if they
want to use this approach is there
anything that we miss that you'd like to
mention so just a couple of things we've
got a growing worldwide partner program
with team topologies which is proving
increasingly successful and useful
around the world and if you're
interested in joining that let us know
there's opportunities for organizations
and opportunities for individuals as
team prodes Advocates and if you're
interested in the aspect of active
knowledge diffusion that I mentioned
before where we're we're running
conferences and and and engaging people
and increasing alignment then get in
touch with me and my company conflex as
well can can help on that if you want to
get in contact with me I'm at Matthew
skeleton. comom that's the easiest place
to find me we'll put some information in
in the links of this episode so you know
thank you Matthew for coming to the show
it's been actually quite a pleasure I
really enjoy the conversation and this
is joavan pron for software engineering
radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of bie
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening